Guide to the Sidney Kaufman Papers ALBA.058
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sidney Kaufman Papers
1937-1945, (Bulk 1937-1939)
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kaufman, Sidney
ALBA.058
0.5 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Sidney Kaufman served in the International Brigades in Spain from July 1937 through February 1939. Kaufman later served in World War II transporting troops in the South Pacific. He was a lifelong member of the Marine Cooks and Stewards Union and the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union. The collection contains Kaufman's correspondence, mementos, military documents, and newspaper articles, primarily dating from his time in Spain.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from Brandeis University, January 2001.
Provenance
The Sidney Kaufman Papers were donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Sidney Kaufman between 1977 and 1979 in three different accessions. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Sidney Kaufman was born in 1914. He was a merchant seaman working out of New York when he decided to volunteer for the International Brigades in Spain. Arriving in Spain in July 1937, Kaufman served as a runner with the British battalion, spent several months in the 35th artillery battery, and was commissar of an anti-tank battery attached to the Slavic battalion on the Aragon Front. In January 1939, when most International Brigaders were making their way out of the country, Kaufman was trapped in Barcelona as Franco's forces prepared to enter the city. Kaufman spent the following three weeks traveling the countryside, searching for a means of escape. In February, he finally made it over the border into France, only to be held in a French detention camp for several days before being granted passage home. Kaufman later served in World War II transporting troops in the South Pacific. A lifelong member of the Marine Cooks and Stewards Union and the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, Kaufman retired in 1979.
Sources:
Elizabeth C. Compa, "Sid Kaufman's Odyssey out of Spain," The Volunteer, June 2005.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of letters and postcards from Kaufman to his parents and others, as well as letters to Kaufman in Spain; military orders (the bulk of which are in Spanish); newspaper articles; propaganda of the International Brigades and the Partit Socialista Unificat (P.S.U.), including a pop-up card; a fascist propaganda leaflet; and other items. Of particular note is a journal Kaufman kept during the period when he was searching for a way out of Spain. Kaufman's scrapbook, located at the end of the collection, contains items from the Spanish Civil War, including letters, postcards, newspaper articles, stamps, tickets, and other mementos. Material from World War II includes a V-Mail with a cartoon by Spanish Civil War veteran Vincent Lossowski and clippings about Lossowski and other International Brigades veterans in World War II.
Arrangement
Series I is arranged alphabetically; the scrapbook has been placed at the end of the collection.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I. Spanish Civil War and World War II.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Separated Material
Audiocassettes from the Sidney Kaufman Collection have been transferred to the audio section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library. On the recordings, made in 1977, Kaufman reads portions of and discusses the journal contained in this collection.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Barcelona (Spain); Scrapbooks.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- International brigades.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Correspondence.; Personal papers.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Articles.; Lossowski, Vincent, 1914-1984; Partit Socialista Unificat de Catalunya; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Kaufman, Sidney; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV
- Series I: Spanish Civil War and World War II.
  - Clippings, Nov 1938, Jan 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Commission Militaire Internationale: French detention camp document, Feb 1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Incoming, Sep 1937-Mar 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing, undated, Jul 1937-Apr 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fascist propaganda: Leaflet, ca.1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - International Brigades: Company notes (handwritten), undated, Aug 1937-Jun 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - International Brigades: Orders of the Day, authorizations, communiqués, undated, Oct 1937-Oct 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Brigades propaganda: Postcards and other graphics, undated, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Kaufman, Sidney: Journal, Jan 1939-Feb 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Leaflets, handbills, and tickets, undated, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mementos: Postcard, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Partit Socialista Unificat (P.S.U.): Leaflet, clipping, card, undated, Feb 1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Socorro Rojo Internacional: Postcard, note, receipt, undated, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - World War II: Clippings, V-mail, Dec 1942-Nov 1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook pages, undated, Aug 1937-Nov 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook (Box 2)